<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Portals Bridges Home Page</title>
    <subtitle>Welcome to Portals Bridges</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="Ate Douma" email="ate@douma.nu"/>
    </authors>
  </properties>
  <body>
<section name="Overview">
      <p>
      Portals Bridges provides support for <a href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=168" target="_nw">JSR-168</a> compliant
      Portlet development using common web frameworks like Struts, JSF, PHP, Perl, Velocity and Groovy.  
      </p>
      <subsection name="JavaServer Faces">
      <p>
	  JavaServer Faces (JSF) applications can be run within an Portlet environment with little or no changes using the <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-jsf/index.html">JSF bridge</a>
      which provides a JSFPortlet ready to be deployed.
      Similar functionality is also available from the <a href='http://myfaces.apache.org/portlet-bridge/index.html'>Apache MyFaces PortletBridge</a>.  
      This bridge is the reference implementation for <a href='http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=301'>JSR 301: Portlet Bridge for JavaServer Faces</a>.
	</p>      
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Struts and PHP">
      </subsection>
      <p>
      Pure servlet based frameworks like Struts or PHP 4 (with the Java binding) are very difficult to use in a
      Portlet environment because they only support and understand a single request event.
      </p>
      <p>
      For a Portlet, the request processing has to be handled in two separated action and render events. Furthermore,
      the Portlet Specification doesn't allow servlet access during the action request event.
      </p>
      <p>
      A distinctive feature of the Portals Bridges is that it removes these barriers and thereby allows the mapping of
      an action request event to the underlying servlet handler implementation (e.g. a StrutsAction).
      </p>
      <p>
      All that is needed is an implementation of the generic ServletContextProvider interface, provided with The Portals
      Bridges <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-common/index.html">Common</a> library, for a specific Portal.
      </p>
      <p>
      The <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-struts/index.html">Portals Struts Bridge</a> furthermore provides a truly transparent mapping of the two request events
      onto the underlying Struts Action mappings and enables an existing Struts Application to be run within a Portlet context
      with very little changes.
      </p>
      <p>
      The following table contains a list of Portals already known to support this solution:
      </p>
      <table> 
      <tr>
        <th>Portal</th>
        <th>License</th>
        <th>Support</th>
        <th>Comment</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td nowrap="true"><a href="http://portals.apache.org/jetspeed-2" target="_nw">Jetspeed 2 Enterprise Portal</a></td>
        <td>Apache</td>
        <td>Native</td>
        <td>All the Apache Portals Bridges are developed using Jetspeed 2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td nowrap="true"><a href="http://portals.apache.org/jetspeed-1" target="_nw">Jetspeed 1 Enterprise Portal</a></td>
        <td>Apache</td>
        <td>Native (Fusion)</td>
        <td>The 1.6 Fusion release provides JSR-168 support using Jetspeed 2 as embedded portlet container</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><a href="http://www.jboss.org/products/jbossportal" target="_nw">JBoss Portal</a></td>
        <td>LGPL</td>
        <td>Native</td>
        <td>The Struts Bridge is provided with JBoss Portal 2.0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><a href="http://www.gridsphere.org" target="_nw">GridSphere Portal</a></td>
        <td>GridSphere Open License</td>
        <td>Native</td>
        <td>The Struts Bridge is provided with Gridsphere Portal 2.1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><a href="http://www.nabh.com/projects/sbportal" target="_nw">Stringbeans Portal</a></td>
        <td>GPL, Commercial</td>
        <td>Native</td>
        <td>The Struts Bridge is provided with Stringbeans Portal 2.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><a href="http://www.vignette.com" target="_nw">Vignette Application Portal</a></td>
        <td>Commercial</td>
        <td>Custom</td>
        <td>The Struts Bridge is successfully used with VAP 7.x</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><a href="http://cocoon.apache.org" target="_nw">Apache Cocoon Portal</a></td>
        <td>Apache</td>
        <td>Native</td>
        <td>The Struts Bridge is successfully used with the latest Cocoon Portal engine.</td>
      </tr>
      </table>
      <subsection name="Velocity">
      <p>
      Although JavaServer Pages (JSP) are very much promoted for Portlet View rendering, other technologies can be
      used just as easily. The <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-velocity/index.html">Portals Velocity Bridge</a> provides several ready to use Velocity based
      Portlets, together with a library of useful scripts. 
      </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Groovy">
      <p>
        The <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-groovy/index.html">Groovy Portlet Bridge</a> allows using groovy scripting for rapid portlet development.
        A groovy script portlet can be implemented like Java-based portlets, and so developers can use any techniques used in Java.
        For example, a groovy script portlet can extend org.apache.portals.bridges.common.GenericServletPortlet to simplify implementation.
        Therefore, GroovyPortlet is very simple, but it will be very useful for developers.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Perl">
      <p>
      Perl based web applications can be accessed as a Portlet using the <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-perl/index.html">Portals Perl Bridge</a>.
      </p>
      <subsection name="Common Utilities and Interfaces">
      <p>
      The <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-common/index.html">Portals Bridges Common</a> library provides, besides
      the already mentioned ServletContextProvider interface, several additional utilities like a GenericServletPortlet
      which you can use for simple JSP based Portlets (or any invokable view Render technology). Or use it as base
      class for your own Bridge.
      </p>
      <p>
      Other useful utilities included are a PreferenceHelper and a simple PortletMessaging component.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="PortletFilter">
      <p>
        The <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-portletfilter/index.html">Portlet Filter</a> provides a FilterPortlet which
        enables you to add processes to run before and after accessing the target portlet.
        The feature provided by FilterPortlet is like a Servlet Filter. (Portlet Filter may be included in
        the future Portlet Spec, but currently it's not included yet.) 
      </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Examples">
      <p>
      Several examples using the bridges are available:
      <ul>
        <li>The <a href="multiproject/jsf-demo/index.html">JSF Portlet Demo</a> application using the JSF Portlet Bridge</li>
        <li>The <a href="multiproject/jpetstore/index.html">iBATIS JPetstore Demo Portlet</a> application using the Struts Portlet Bridge</li>
        <li>The <a href="multiproject/php/index.html">PHP Portlet</a> application</li>
        <li>The <a href="multiproject/perl/index.html">Perl Portlet</a> application</li>
        <li>The <a href="multiproject/portals-bridges-andromda-struts/index.html">Andromda Struts demo portlet</a> application created using the Andromda BPM4Struts cartridge</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
      Furhermore, Jetspeed 2 makes full use of bridges. For example have a look at:
      <ul>
        <li>The <a href="http://portals.apache.org/jetspeed-2/multiproject/j2-admin" target="_nw">Jetspeed-2 Administration</a> using the Velocity Bridge</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      </subsection>
</section>
>
  </body>
</document>
